{"tossups": [{"question": "This region was once divided into three kingdoms, one of which was Yeren. One native of this region suppressed a rebellion under the Prince of Gui, and this region is divided from a nation its natives conquered by the (*)  Willow Palisade. This region's people were led by Dorgon, a leader of the Kingdom of Haixi. One \"incident\" that took place in this region involved a bomb set by Suemori Kawamoto, and this region was the site of a siege at which Oskar Stark's fleet was defeated. This region was the location of a Japanese puppet state ruled by Emperor Puyi, the last emperor of a dynasty sometimes named for this region. For ten points, name this region whose natives established the Qing Dynasty.", "answer": "Manchuria  (accept Manchoukuo)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Manchuria</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Manchuria", "Manchuria"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Manchoukuo"}, {"question": "This empire collapsed after its final ruler proposed to a powerful governor's daughter and was rebuffed. Chancellor Bolad provided crucial source material for one history commissioned by one of this empire's rulers, and this empire's ruling dynasty married into the Byzantine royal family through Michael VIII's daughter, (*)  Marina Palaiologina. One ruler of this empire was baptized as Nicholas despite his father's conversion to Islam, and Chupan was a critical power broker in the later years of this empire after the death of Rashid al-Din Hamadani. This empire's founder's army lost the battle of Ain Jalut. For ten points, name this Mongol successor state, ruled at times by Abu Sa'id, Oljeitu, Gazan, and Hulagu Khan.", "answer": " Il-Khanate  (accept  Hulagu 's Khanate until \"Hulagu\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Il-Khanate</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Il-Khanate", "Il-Khanate"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  Hulagu 's Khanate until \"Hulagu\""}, {"question": "One leading figure of opposition to this man shot himself in the abdomen on radio as a commercial for coffee that was \"good to the last stomachful\" was playing. That man was Eddy Chibas, who led the (*)  Orthodox Party. Another opposition group against this man was the Federation of University Students, led by a student nicknamed \"Manzanita\". This man ceded control of his capital's casinos to Mayer Lansky, giving that capital the nickname of \"Latin Las Vegas\". This man overthrew one of his predecessors, Gerardo Machado, in the \"Revolt of the Sergeants\". For ten points, name this Cuban dictator overthrown by Fidel Castro.", "answer": "Fulgencio  Batista  Zaldivar", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Fulgencio  Batista  Zaldivar</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Fulgencio  Batista  Zaldivar", "Fulgencio  Batista  Zaldivar"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Thomas Dillehay had a group of critics flown in from the US to Chile to investigate his proposal of a site that predated this. Another such proposal is based on nine turds found in a cave. Another site claimed to predate this one based is named for   Debra L. Friedkin, and a migration predating the one that produced this site may have arrived (*)  by boat. This site that this theory is named for was not excavated for three years after its discovery by a Native American teenager. Evidence for the theory that this site's namesake culture was not the first in the Americas has come from Buttermilk Creek, Paisley Caves, and Meadowcroft. For ten points, name this site in New Mexico widely believed to mark the first arrival of humans in the Americas.", "answer": "Clovis", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Clovis</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Clovis", "Clovis"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "According to Chinese government annals, these people had rock sugar put in their mouths and gum on their palms at birth. Kang Senghui, a member of this ethnic group, was a prominent translator of Buddhist scriptures, and (*)  the \"nine golden surnames\" of these people include An, Shi, and Cao. The namesake \"rock\" of these people was captured after Alexander the Great offered a hefty reward to the first man to summit it. The father of An Lushan was one of these people, and his name is probably a sinicization of their name, \"rukhsan\". The feminine version of that name belonged to Alexander the Great's wife, one of these people. For ten points, name these people whose language Paul Pelliot called \"the Lingua Franca of the Silk Road\".", "answer": "Sogdian  (prompt on \"Persian\", accept \"Su-li\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sogdian</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sogdian", "Sogdian"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \"Persian\", accept \"Su-li\""}, {"question": "This organization was demonized by Gov. Sidney Catts of Florida. He argued that they were planning to build a new headquarters in San Antonio by sparking a pro-German black revolt. The Tallulah Lynchings targeted Italian-Americans due to their membership in this group. This organization (*)  was the target of the Bloody Monday riots in Louisville, and the first diplomatic mission of this organization to the United States was cancelled after its leader was blamed for the death of an anarchist. John Jay recommended building \"a wall of brass\" to keep members of this organization out of the United States, predating Donald Trump by at least two centuries. For ten points, name this organization that Al Smith was the first major presidential candidate to belong to.", "answer": "Catholic  Church", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Catholic  Church</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Catholic  Church", "Catholic  Church"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Most historians believe that this title was held at times by an interrex and was elective, which would explain why its holders' average reign was over 40 years. One holder of this title had the name of his father omitted from his entry on a list of successful generals because that man was the son of a slave. This title (*)  was also held by the husband of Tanaquil as well as a man who built the seaport at Ostia. Early holders of this title warred with the city of Alba Longa, and Titus Tatius ruled alongside the first holder of this title. This title was eschewed by later rulers of its namesake city-unsurprising given the fate of its last ruler, Tarquinius Superbus. For ten points, name this title held by seven people including Numa Pompilius, Servius Tulius, and Romulus.", "answer": "King of Rome  (do NOT accept \"Emperor\" or \"consul\")", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>King of Rome</u></b>", "acceptable": ["King of Rome", "King of Rome"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "do NOT accept \"Emperor\" or \"consul\""}, {"question": "One kingdom based in this modern-day country built a capital whose main gate is shaped like a lion's paws. A ruler of another kingdom based on this island created a reservoir known as his namesake \"sea\". This (*)  country is home to the Temple of the Tooth, and this country's highest point is the sacred mountain of Adam's Peak. This country is home to the Australoid Vedda people, and it was the site of a Portuguese and subsequently, Dutch colony at Galle. This country elected the world's first female leader of a democracy. The Kingdom of Kandy was located in this modern-day country, as was a kingdom centered at Polonnaruwa. For ten points, name this island nation riven by a civil war between Tamils and Sinhalese.", "answer": "Democratic Republic of  Sri Lanka  (prompt on Ceylon)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Democratic Republic of  Sri <b><u>Lanka</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Democratic Republic of  Sri Lanka", "Lanka"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Ceylon"}, {"question": "This country was the site of a siege of its parliament by Jamaat al-Muslimeen militants, and one of its islands was colonized by a duchy in which Catherine the Great was born. This country (*)  is separated from the mainland by the Dragon's Mouth,and during the Napoleonic Wars, it was taken by France from Spain, then y by Britain,. Its two main islands were often raided for slaves by Spanish pearl fishers based in Venezuela, and it is currently lead by Kamla Persad-Bisesar. Calypso music originated in this country. For ten points, name this Caribbean nation whose main island is named after the Spanish for \"trinity\".", "answer": "Trinidad and Tobago", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Trinidad and <b><u>Tobago</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Trinidad and Tobago", "Tobago"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During the Tang and Song Dynasties, the Chinese government monopolized iron and this commodity which inspired Huan Guan to write Discourses on this commodity  and Iron. This commodity was produced in great quantities at Aigues-Mortes, and (*)  the Halstatt culture derived much of its wealth from trading this commodity. The city of Taghaza was a mining center for this commodity, and one march named for this commodity reached the sea at the town of Dandi. For ten points, name this commodity, manufactured in part by evaporating seawater in pools called  sebkhas.", "answer": "salt", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>salt</u></b>", "acceptable": ["salt", "salt"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "ne founding member of this organization had his headquarters at Norman's Cay. Richard Novak, a marine biologist and the island's former divemaster, conducted a sabotage operation against him there. This organization formed a sub-group to combat a decree by Pres. Belisario Betancur, and it (*) repeatedly offered to pay the external debt of the country in which it operated. One leader nicknamed \"La Pina\" offered asylum to the leader of this group. The \"Los Pepes\" vigilante group rarely agreed with this organization, which it was formed to combat. This organization's original name was \"Death to Kidnappers\". For ten points, name this organization once led by Pablo Escobar, chronicled in the television drama  Narcos and named after a Colombian city.", "answer": "Medellin  Cartel", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Medellin  Cartel</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Medellin  Cartel", "Medellin  Cartel"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This alphabet is used to write the Cia-Cia language, which is spoken in a chain of islands off Sulawesi. This alphabet is also known by a term that translates as \"writing one can learn in a morning\", and one (*)  reformer of this alphabet brutally suppressed a general strike on his country's largest island. This alphabet is transliterated using the McCune-Reischauer system, and was banned under a cultural assimilation policy before the outbreak of World War II. This alphabet is known by two different names in the two countries in which it is official, and was created by the Scholars of the Jade Hall. For ten points, name this alphabet whose creation was commissioned by Sejong the Great and is used to write Korean.", "answer": "Hangul", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hangul</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hangul", "Hangul"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this country, a leader of the Freethinkers' Party established a military dictatorship in the years leading up to WWII. This country's monarchy      was established by a cadet branch of the House of Wittelsbach, and Winston Churchill said of (*)  the death of one of its kings that \"a quarter million died of that monkey's bite\". This country's founding leader was the first man before Eduard Shevardnadze to be the foreign minister of one country, then Prime Minister of another. This country, along with one to its East, was the first recipient of aid under the Truman doctrine, and a fascist party in this country lost popularity after being linked to the murder of a popular rapper. This country's Syriza Party has held power since 2014. For ten points, name this country led at various times by Ioannis Kapodistrias, Ioannis Metaxas, and Alexis Tsipras.", "answer": "Greece", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Greece</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Greece", "Greece"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A radio DJ in this country played the song \"Heartbreaker\" to interrupt the announcement of a coup, and this country sent census takers into nomadic camps in a disputed region, thus initiating the Christmas War. In a popular epigram, the Soviet (*)  Union was compared to this country \"with rockets\". It's not Morocco, but one kingdom based in this country sacked Timbuktu in a war against the Songhai. This country's capital city shares a name with the ruling house of one of its Mossi Kingdoms. This country was renamed to a native term meaning 'Land of Honest Men\" by President Thomas Sankara. For ten points, name this country, formerly known as Upper Volta, whose capital is Ouagadougou.", "answer": "Burkina Faso  (accept  Upper Volta  until those words are said.)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Burkina <b><u>Faso</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Burkina Faso", "Faso"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  Upper Volta  until those words are said."}, {"question": "One man with this characteristic was used as a specimen in a museum after his death, and belonged to the same Masonic lodge as Mozart and Schubert. Another man    with this characteristic established a fortress at Janjira          that remained unconquered by the  (*)Marathas and the British, from whom it requested that it remain independent from India. Another man with this characteristic, Abram Gannibal, convinced Alexander Suvorov's father to allow young Alexander to pursue a military career. He was the great-grandfather of Alexander Pushkin. The founder of a philosophical school named for this characteristic was Aime Cesaire. Another man with this characteristic, Onesimus, worked with Cotton Mather to introduce smallpox immunization to the US. For ten points, name this characteristic shared by former slaves such as Malik Ambar and Angelo Soliman.", "answer": "they were all  black  (accept  African )", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>they were all  black</u></b>", "acceptable": ["they were all  black", "they were all  black"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  African"}, {"question": "Eusebius deepened the schism between Catholicism and Arianism by doing this with St. Nicholas' cloak. It's not jumping, but Cai Yuan and Jian Jun Xi did this on an art installation in London. The Emperor Caracalla was murdered by a disgruntled soldier while doing this in a street. Winston Churchill (*)  did this on the banks of the Rhine and the Siegfried Line after British troops secured them, and Jean-Jacques Rousseau wrote of doing this in a neighbor's cooking pot in his Confessions. For ten points, a fountain in Brussels known as Manneken Pis depicts a boy doing this.", "answer": "Urinating  (accept  peeing )", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Urinating</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Urinating", "Urinating"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  peeing"}, {"question": "One coup in this country was postponed for an Umm Khaltoum concert. Several IRA operatives left this country after they realized they were being trained in desert fighting, and this country is the staging ground of Operation Dignity. Parts of this country (*)  were united with Crete in a Roman province, and the Green Guards operated in this country. Much of this country is held by militias that       represent the Toubou People, and the United Arab Emirates recently began airstrikes on this country. This country is home to a brotherhood of Sufis known as the Sanussis, and was once ruled by King Idris I. For ten points, name this country once ruled by Muammar Qaddafi.", "answer": "Libya", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Libya</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Libya", "Libya"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "French colonists referred to the Southern part of this country as \"Useful\" this country, and one empire centered in this country was chronicled in the  Girgam. That empire converted to Islam under Emperor Hummay. That conversion caused the (*)  Zaghawa people to flee this country. One former leader of this country was convicted of Crimes against Humanity by the Extraordinary African Chambers in May 2016. That leader won a war centered around the cities of Faya-Largeau and Ouadi Doum in the Toyota War. This country's Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti region is adjacent to the disputed region that provoked that war. For ten points, name this country formerly ruled by Hissene Habre, whose border with Nigeria runs through its namesake lake.", "answer": "Chad", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Chad</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Chad", "Chad"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One rebellion in this state was caused by a state law that required voters to own at least $134 in property. One of this state's settlements was founded by a woman who ignited the Antinomian Controversy in her home colony. That rebellion was led by Thomas Wilson Dorr. (*) The founder of this colony wrote  A Key into the Language of America. This state's longest-ever serving senator founded a program of college grants for the poor. That man was Claiborne Pell. For ten points, name this colony founded by Roger Williams, the name of whose corresponding modern state is paired in its name with \"Providence Plantations\".", "answer": "Rhode Island  and Providence Plantations", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Rhode Island  and Providence Plantations</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Rhode Island  and Providence Plantations", "Rhode Island  and Providence Plantations"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One president of this country, Edwin Barclay, won an election with over twice as many votes as the population of this country. This country was the subject of a libretto by Melvin Tolbert, and one leader of this country loosened tax laws and registration restrictions, giving this country the world's largest merchant marine. Another leader of this country (*)  filmed himself eating that man's ear. This country sent troops to assist a fellow Anglophonic country in fighting the Revolutionary United Front, and this country's dominant party for over a century was the True Whigs. It's not the United States, but one of this country's administrative divisions is named Maryland. This country was the site of a civil war between Samuel Doe and Prince Johnson. For 10 points, name this country settled by former American slaves whose descendants are this country's ruling class.", "answer": "Liberia", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Liberia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Liberia", "Liberia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}